A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- SERIES I. LETTERS & MANUSCRIPTS
  - Thomas Nairne to Charles, Earl of Sunderland 1708 Jul 18, ALS, 5p. (Box 7)
    Writes as an agent and itinerary Justice among the Indians, appointed by the General Assembly of South Carolina, concerning his investigation into the strengths of the Indian tribes in the lands belonging to the colony of South Carolina that could possibly be united by the French settled at Mobile against the colony and makes suggestions about future settlement and trade; #1178
  - [Abner Nash], Governor of North Carolina, to "Gentlemen" 1780 Aug 23, AL (Box 7)
    Describes the Battle of Camden, South Carolina and the defeat of General Sumter at Hanging Rock; #3620
  - Noel and Hazard to Eleazor Wheelock 1771 Oct 25, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Discuss the possible sale of books and mathematical instruments to Dartmouth College, advertise their connections to New Jersey College, and credit terms; #10547-cd
  - 1774 May 30, AMsS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Call for a Town Meeting in Norwich, Connecticut, signed by selectmen Thomas Gray, Benjamin Huntington, Barnabas Huntington, and Elijah Brewster, to discuss ways to show and promote loyalty to the king; #10547-ce
  - Francis Turner Palgrave to "Sir" 1876 Dec 23, ALS, 2p. (Box 7)
    Grants permission to print whatever poems the recipient likes but asks that he include "Thou that once"; #10547-cf
  - J.W. Parmalee to his friend, Wheeler 1848-1850, 3 ALS (Box 7)
    Parmalee, a South Carolina businessman, writes concerning life in Charleston, travel through North Carolina, Tennessee, Georgia and Alabama on business trips, with anecdotes about the Revolutionary War from places visited; news of friends and Dartmouth College, and comments about national politics, North versus the South, and slavery; #10547-cg
  - Unpublished Memorandum from the Count de Penalosa (1624- 1687) 1675, AM, 12p. (Box 7)
    Urging King Louis XIV to conquer and colonize New Mexico rather than Canada; #1708
  - Edmund Pendleton to James Madison 1780 Nov 20, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Writes that he has not heard anything lately from the Southern Army but General Green passed through Virginia the last Wednesday in haste and reports on the comments of a deserter from the enemy who lived in Delaware who believed the enemy to be embarking for either New York or Charleston; #3643
  - U.S. State Department Circular to Consuls and Vice-Consuls, signed by Timothy Pickering, to Richard O'Brien 1798 Nov 10 (Box 7)
    #495
  - Edgar Allan Poe, New York, to Edward Valentine 184[8] Nov 20, ALS, 2p., with envelope. Photocopy. (Box 7)
    Asks Valentine to lend him two hundred dollars to enable him to establish a new magazine called The Stylus and sends him a prospectus about the magazine; #5153-a
  - Walter Alexander Raleigh to Walter Edwin Peck 1920-1921, 2 ALS (Box 7)
    Comments on quarrels between authors and editors, and mentions Thomas Jefferson Hogg, Mark Twain, Harriet Westbrook Shelley, and American airmen learning to fly at a local R.A.F. base; #10547-ch
  - Speech by John Randolph of Roanoke, with autograph corrections and interlinear notations attributed to Thomas Jefferson, comprising about 520 words, accompanied by a small sheet bearing longer notes about the speech, also in Jefferson's hand 1820 Mar 3, AMs (Box 7)
  - John Randolph of Roanoke to Washington Irving 1831 Aug 22, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Seriously considering sailing on The Hannibal, which leaves London on the 25th, and asks if he need to make any arrangement with Customs for himself or if Irving has any "commands for the United States"; #2832
  - Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Nahum Capen 1873-1874, 4 ALS (Box 7)
    Discusses the election of Abraham Lincoln, the loyalty of many Virginia leaders to the Union before the Civil War, and the deep fear of a slave insurrection caused by the raid of John Brown upon its citizens (1873 Apr 11); the separation of church and state essential to promotion of democracy, illustrated by a history lesson (1873 Apr 21); the progress of Reconstruction and its effects in Louisiana and the inflammatory intent of the book The Impending Crisis of the South and John Brown's raid who was glorified in the North (1873 May 22); praises Capen's book The History of Democracy in the United States and comments on the Tidewater aristocracy in Virginia as compared to that of New England; #1596
  - Letters to Thomas Mann Randolph from applicants seeking work on the survey of the Florida boundary 1826, 22 ALS (Box 7)
  - Law Suit between Thomas Mann Randolph and [heirs of?] Francis W. Gilmer, et al 1827 Aug 4, AD (Box 7)
  - Letters from Sir Walter Scott to James Gibson Craig, Hay Donaldson, Edward Forster, James Robert Hope-Scott, Francis MacKenzie Humberston, Lord Seaforth, John Murray, William Stewart Rose, Thomas Sheridan, and Robert Southey [1803?]-1830, 17 ALS (Box 7)
    Writes concerning his Life of Dryden, William Caxton's Le Morte d'Arthur, Skene's sketches, the playwright Joanna Baillie, a biography of Humphrey Davy, a translation of Orlando Furioso, a meeting with the Prince Regent, publishing ventures, financial affairs, family activities and friends, French politics, Byron, Coleridge, Wordsworth, Archibald Constable and the Royal Society of Scotland; #10547-p
  - Invitation to Sir Walter Scott by Directors of the Caledonian Asylum to be a steward at a dinner benefiting the institution 1825 Feb 3 (Box 7)
    #10547-p
  - Letters of A. Black and James Hope Scott 1871 Oct 27, 2 ALS (Box 7)
    Concerning Sir Walter Scott; #10547-p
  - Engraving and photograph of a Portrait of Sir Walter Scott n.d. (Box 7)
  - Photograph of Abbotsford, the home of Sir Walter Scott n.d. (Box 7)
  - William Wallace Scott to John Hart 1902 Sep 27, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Implores Hart to care for the Virginia State Library while he is at home celebrating his thirty-third wedding anniversary; #10547-ci
  - Letters pertaining to Sebaldus, Baron Schmeling, apparently an imposter, in German 1849-1850, 3 ALS (Box 7)
    #9407-a
  - Samuel Sewall to his wife, Hannah Sewall 1689 Oct 9, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Explains the delays in embarking because of the dangers of attack at sea by the French and expresses his love for her and their family; #10547-cj
  - George Bernard Shaw to G. [Routledge] 1902 Oct 22, ALS (Box 7)
    Complains about the lack of advertisement for his books, especially the revised edition of Cashel Byron's Profession and the poor profit from sales of his works, adding he might take his next book to a different publisher; #10547-ck
  - George Bernard Shaw to Albert Edwin Drinkwater 1913 Jan 5, ANS (Box 7)
    Suggests possible pictorial subjects for use in John Bull's Other Island; #10547-ck
  - Philip Slaughter to "My old Friend" 1886 Jun 30, ALS, 2p. (Box 7)
    Furnishes biographical information concerning John Bracken; #10547-cl
  - Program for the McGregor Room Seminars in Contemporary Prose & Poetry "The Poetry of W.H. Auden" autographed by Theodore Spenser 1947 May 16, print (Box 8)
    #10547-do
  - "The Study of English Literature" by Leslie Stephen 1887, TMs (mimeograph) (Box 8)
    #10547-cm
  - Letters from the files of Henry Stevens from men of note in the book world including, Justin Winsor, Henry Huth, and Henry Harisse 1865-1877, 5 ALS (Box 8)
    #10547-cn
  - Robert Louis Stevenson to his father, Thomas Stevenson 1886 Sep 5, ALS, 2p. (Box 8)
    Refers to his writing a memoir of his friend and teacher, Fleeming Jenkin and a story in French for a French magazine; and offers to buy some of his common port if he throws in some old rum, "old rum is our idol here."; #38-730
  - Letters concerning an Algernon Swinburne forgery supposedly written upon the death of Alfred Lord Tennyson; the forgery is also present 1944-1949, 5 items (Box 8)
    #10547-co
  - John Addington Symonds Letters 1873-1882, 6 ALS (Box 8)
    Writes to his publisher, Smith, Elder & Co., requesting that dedication copies of his works be sent to designated friends; a letter to the Editor of the Academy asking him to print an enclosed notice, "I have found that I could make a better book by selecting sonnets of one tone & issuing these together, leaving the most miscellaneous collection for a future occasion," and also writes concerning his family genealogy; #10547-q
  - John Addington Symonds Photograph 1886 (Box 8)
    The photograph, by Walter L. Colls, was used as a frontispiece for Horatio Brown's 1895 biography of Symonds; #10547-t
  - Benjamin Ogle Tayloe to Mr. McPherson of Carlisle & McPherson 1866 Apr 7, ALS, 4p. (Box 8)
    Writes concerning the details surrounding the seizure of his cotton at Mobile, Alabama for a subscription for a Confederate loan and his attempts to be reimbursed; #10547-cp
  - Alfred Lord Tennyson to Elizabeth Barrett Browning and "My dear Duchess" 1852,1862, 2 ALS (Box 8)
    Expresses gratitude for her note and Robert Browning's Epilogue; and discusses his plans to arrange a meeting with Queen Victoria now that his health is restored; also includes a letter from Thomas J. Wise to Mr. Swann, 1934 February 24, stating that the manuscript of Crossing the Bar is likely in the hand of Emily Tennyson which is similar to her husband's; #10547-cq
  - Tobacco Taxes, Potomac & Patuxent Districts, Maryland 1697-1704 (Box 8)
    #5908
  - Letters to John Payne Todd 1815, 2 ALS, with transcripts (Box 8)
    In the earlier letter, May 31, 1815, E.L. [Lauton ?] on board The Neptune in Plymouth Harbor, asks Todd to write a letter to Julian Touchard at Havre de Grace requesting permission for a French medical student, Armand Lement, to accompany [Lautton ?] to America as a sort of waiting assistant in taking care of Mr. [James Asheton] Bayard (1767-1815) if Mr. [Albert] Gallatin (1761-1849) has no objection. Gallatin was in Great Britain negotiating a commercial treaty for President Madison in 1815.
    The second letter, June 5, 1815, informs Todd since he [G.B.M.] and Todd had separated, Mr. Bayard's condition had worsened to the point of death but he now appeared to be improving. He also tells Todd that The Neptune will sail on June 14th and asks him to pay a debt for him to Preston & Burrows if his finances will allow it; #10547-dk
  - Minutes of the Privy Council in the hand of Charles Townshend 1765 Jul 19-Dec 17, AMs (Box 8)
    Concerning the American colonies; In the summer and fall of 1765, Townshend was Paymaster General and ex officio member of the Privy Council; #10547-cr
  - Anthony Trollope to "My dear Anna" 1861 May 10, ALS, 4p. (Box 8)
    Writes that he had to cut out over 64 pages of his first book and explains the financial reasons why her publisher, Chapman and Hall might want her to cut the length of her book; #10547-di
  - Abiel Holmes to the Rev. Dr. Benjamin Trumball 1802-1814, 5 ALS (Box 8)
    Discusses the work of Trumball, especially his general history of the United States and histories of Massachusetts and Connecticut, and mentions Joseph Emerson, Thomas Ruggles, Claudius Buchanan, and the War of 1812; #10547-r
  - St. George Tucker to John Page 1801 Feb 27, ALS, 3p.; with an undated engraving of Tucker (Box 8)
    Discusses the recent presidential election of Thomas Jefferson, the Federalist Party will throw many obstacles in his path, their appointment of James A. Bayard as minister to France, and Tucker's advocacy of abolishing the office of President in favor of a federal Council of the States; #3640
  - John Tyler to Charles Fenton Mercer 1826 Dec 5, ALS, 3p. (Box 8)
    Discusses internal improvements in Virginia as described in his message to the citizens just sent to the printers, and his high opinion of Colonel Gamble exceeded only by that of Claudius Crozet, "But you undervalue Crozet - rely on it that I am not deceived when I pronounce him inferior to no man in Virginia for that quality which old George Mason esteemed so highly, real sagacity - added to which he is a man of the most extensive research, and profound science - But above all I regard him as honest - His candor has caused him to be sometimes unpopular in particular sections"; #2510-a
  - Engraving of Sir Henry Vane see Prints File-Vane n.d., print (Box 8)
    #10547-dg
  - Copy of the Virginia House of Burgesses Act prohibiting the desertion of Plantations made by William Robertson, Clerk of the Virginia Council, 1705-1720 1644 Feb 17, AMsS (Box 8)
    #2261
  - Virginia-North Carolina Manuscript Road Maps 1779 May-Jun, AMs (Box 8)
    Drawn in ink while on a wagon trip from the Catawba River in western North Carolina to the Potomac River in Virginia, showing intersecting and branch roads, plantations, churches, fords, streams, and inns, near the Road. Consists of 25 itinerary maps in a complete, consecutive series, covering the entire journey through these states on the way to New Jersey, by a member of the Stockton or Eddy family of New Jersey; #1112
  - Lew Wallace to Adjutant General LovE 1860 Sep 7, ALS, 1p. (Box 8)
    Recommends Captain M.J. Fletcher for the position of Love's secretary; #10547-cs
  - Sarah Mather Walter to her daughter, Hannah Walter Trowbridge [1720] & n.d., 2 ALS (Box 8)
    Discusses news of family and friends, includes handwritten transcripts of the letters, genealogical notes on the Mather family and news clippings; #10547-ct
  - David Ramsey to Henry Dana Ward 1796 Aug 31 (Box 8)
    Ramsay replies to a letter from Ward concerning the piping of water from the Wando River to Charleston, S.C., to supply domestic needs and to douse fires; #10547-dm
  - Diary describing Daniel Webster's visit to Monticello, and discussing Thomas Jefferson, but not written by Webster [1825 Dec], AMs, 18p. (Box 8)
    #5205
  - Noah Webster to Jedidiah Morse 1796 Apr 23, ALS, 1p. (Box 8)
    Offers his advice on how to improve Morse's American Gazetteer published in 1797, by incorporating some of Scott's work on Connecticut and the middle states; #7895-a
  - Noah Webster to Jedidiah Morse 1796 Dec 7, ALS, 2p. (Box 8)
    Discusses the terms of printing Morse's American Gazetteer, including the type and page size; #7610
  - Mason L. ("Parson") Weems to Thomas Cummings 1822 Aug 26, ALS, 3p. (Box 8)
    Writes concerning financial affairs; #5589
  - Pamphlet containing four sermons delivered by the Rev. Noah Welles in Connecticut 1747-1748, AMs (Box 8)
    #10547-cw
  - Carlton Frank Wells to Tracy W. McGregor [1934] Nov 20, ALS, 2p. (Box 8)
    Discusses the pronunciation of the name of John Donne and includes a copy of a letter from Wells to Henry Seidel Canby on the same subject; #10547-cu
  - Herbert George Wells to "My Dear Sir" and Edith Bell 1896, 1906, 2 ALS (Box 8)
    Writes to a publisher asking if Hall Caine accepted the same conditions for his manuscript as they have proposed to him, and mentions a serial, "Wheels of Chance," appearing in Today which he wishes to place in an American publication as well as about a dozen stories; he asks for the support of Bell in an upcoming controversy; #10547-cv
  - James McNeill Whistler to G.R. Dennis, including an incomplete clipping 1903, n.d., ALS, 2p. (Box 8)
    Furnishes the text of a telegram and requests Dennis make more copies of the telegram and add information to ridicule an editor who wrote an uncomplimentary article about him; #10547-cx
  - Copies of the watercolor drawings by Governor John White, of sixteenth century American Indians, flora, and fauna, originally done ca. 1586 while White was living in the colony on Roanoke Island, in North Carolina. 1935, 63 watercolors (Box 8)
    #38-762
  - Photographic reproductions of drawings by John White n.d., 3 black & white photos (Box 8)
  - Notes on his Hollandic & English parentage and Notes re the composition of Leaves of Grass by Walt Whitman n.d., 2 AMs (Box 8)
    #9778
  - Deed for land in Stamford, Fairfield County, Connecticut, from Amos Whittemore to Jonathan [Waltbie?] 1722 Jan 18, Located in oversize box X-1 (Box 8)
    #10547-dh
  - John Greenleaf Whittier, to Dr.& Mrs. Bowditch 1852-1883, 3 ALS (Box 8)
    Declining a visit due to health and mentioning "spiritual handwriting"; to an unidentified recipient, praising a book of poems received and mentioning Sarah Smiley and Dean Stanley; and to Charles H. Allen concerning affairs in Egypt, the slave trade, and American freedmen; #10547-cy
  - Typescript Copy of Two Resolutions concerning religion in New England, Samuel Willard, Moderator, approved by general conventions in Boston, and signed by various prominent New Englanders, including Cotton Mather [1704, 1706], TMs, copies (Box 8)
    #10547-cz
  - Photograph of Henry Williamson's private field, woods, and work shack a mile northwest of Georgeham [Great Britain] n.d., Black & white photo (Box 8)
    #10547-da
  - Alexander Wilson, father of American ornithology, to Daniel H. Miller, a Philadelphia ironmonger 1808 Dec 24, ALS, 2p. (Box 8)
    Describes part of his canvassing tour from Maine to Georgia to get subscribers for his American Ornithology, focusing on Maryland and Washington, D.C., where he mentions the variety of characters he encountered, the wretched condition of slaves along his journey, and his visit with Thomas Jefferson who gave him a letter of introduction to a gentleman in Virginia acquainted with a someone who had spent his whole life studying the habits of birds; #8133
  - Alexander Wilson to Daniel H. Miller 1809 Feb 15, ALS, 8p. (Box 8)
    Relates the death of George Duncan in Norfolk, Virginia, by yellow fever, and continues with his description of his canvassing tour to sell American Ornithology from Norfolk southward; describes the streets of Norfolk full of water and mud and the flooded conditions elsewhere, fever at Suffolk, hunting rare birds at Murfeesboro, the products of North Carolina, including tar, turpentine, hogs and apple brandy, "a tumbler of which is their morning beverage as soon as they get out of bed," the roads along coastal North Carolina winding through stagnant ponds swarming with alligators, enormous cypress swamps, "the rich Nabob rice planters who live among large villages of their Negroes," who were so hospitable Wilson claimed he could hardly get away again, the deep sands of South Carolina, a trade for "a very devil" of a horse, the climate of Charleston, South Carolina, and as "to the infamous and execrable system of slavery of the Southern states, it has debased not only the slaves but their masters"; #6209-a
  - George Parker Winship to John H. Edmunds 1918 Jan 30, ALS, 1p. (Box 8)
    Sends a book in appreciation for Edmunds' contribution to the Memoir of Frederick Lewis Gay, includes undated list of books; #10547-db
  - James Wood, acting Governor of Virginia, to Brigadier General Joseph Jones, commander of the Virginia Militia at Petersburg 1794 Sep 30, ALS, 1p. (Box 8)
    Writes concerning the Whiskey Rebellion; #10547-dc
  - Legal & Financial Papers of four Connecticut business partners, Dudley Woodbridge of Norwich, Giles Mumford of New London, Wait Rathbun of Stonington, and Joseph Woodbridge, of Groton, who outfitted privateers and ran ships through the British blockade during the Revolutionary War 1777-1782, 29 items (Box 8)
    Containing receipts, accounts, and bills of sales, and mentioning ships Recovery, Sally, Lydia, Betsy, York, Little William, American Revenue, Hero, and Bunker Hill and copies of letters from Dudley Woodbridge to John Welles concerning the ship Recovery(1780); #10547-dd
  - Robert Woodford to Robert Dundas 1809 May 23, ALS, 1p. (Box 8)
    Discusses the disposition of articles once smuggled into New Spain by France; #10547-de
  - William Wordsworth to Thomas Powell and Allan Cunningham 1823-1841, 8 ALS (Box 8)
    Writes to Cunningham concerning busts of Sir Walter Scott, [Samuel] Coleridge, and Robert Southey, and discusses his own poetry; letters to Powell, discuss the Copyright Bill, many details about Wordsworth's revision of Chaucer, his poor eyesight, a play by Leigh Hunt, Sir Robert Peel, and The Monthly Chronicle; #10547-s
  - Legal & Financial Papers of the Wormeley Family, Middlesex County, Virginia, consisting of statements, bills of exchange, bonds, accounts, notes, drafts, deeds, agreements, and letters. 1766-1814, 44 items (Box 8)
    Correspondents include: John Wormeley to Hercules Mulligan and Mr. & Mrs. Allen; Burr Powell to [John Wormeley?]; Ralph Wormeley to Isaac Kent; Forrest S. Stoddert to Ralph Wormeley; Ralph Wormeley to Captain Presley N. O' Bannon; Mann Page to Willoughby Morgan; and Ralph Wormeley to Willoughby Morgan; #1106-b
  - Papers of the Law Firm of George Wythe and Robert Carter Nicholas, Williamsburg, Virginia, re the Carroll vs Clifton Case ca. 1740-1756, ADS (Box 9)
  - Papers of the Law Firm of George Wythe and Robert Carter Nicholas, Williamsburg, Virginia, re the Digges vs Clifton Case 1755-1759, ADS (Box 9)
  - Papers of the Law Firm of George Wythe and Robert Carter Nicholas, Williamsburg, Virginia, re Miscellaneous Chancery Suits ca. 1740-1769, ADS (Box 9)
- SERIES II. BOUND VOLUMES
  - Letterbook of Captain J.T. Champneys, Fort Sumter, South Carolina, April 1862-October 1863 1862-1863 (Box 9)
    Containing daily reports of Champney detailing his supervision of defenses at Fort Sumter during the siege of Charleston, South Carolina, together with six letters, 1861-1863, chiefly re his work as a Confederate ordnance officer, and an undated clipping on the evacuation of St. Simon's Island, Georgia. Correspondents include Major William H. Echols, recipient of most of the reports, Colonel David B. Harris, Major Stephen Elliott, and General Benjamin Hardin Helm. In addition to eighty-five morning reports the letterbook also contains accounts of payrolls and clothing replacements issued. A separate detailed guide to this collection is available. #992
  - Confederate States Army Hospital, Hanover Junction, Invoice Book; later used as a Court Docket Book in Guilford County, North Carolina. 1863-1864, 1866-1868 (Box 9)
    A separate detailed guide to this collection is available. #1159
  - Order Book of the frigate U.S.S. Constellation at [Norfolk?], commanded by Charles Stewart, and including Watch, Quarter, and Station Bill, and Duty Rosters, kept by Lt. James Sanders. [1812?] (Box 9)
    #6071
  - A Brief Abstract re the Question of Precedency between Spain and England collected by Sir Robert Cotton (1571-1631) 1599 (Box 10)
    Cotton's fame as a "master of precedents" spread "so far that in 1600 the queen's advisers referred to him a question of precedency which had arisen between Sir Henry Neville, an English ambassador, and an ambassador from Spain, who were together at Calais discussing the terms of an Anglo-Spanish treaty. Cotton in an elaborate paper decided in favour of his own countryman." ( Dictionary of National Biography"Robert Cotton.") #1011
  - Diary kept by Lt. Salisbury S. Davenport, Regarding his "Travels in Africa, America, West Indies, & France, including Madeira & Tenerife and Central America" 1857-1861, Illustrated with newspaper clippings, engravings and two maps, 290 pages (Box 10)
  - Two letterbooks of Major J.C. Duane, Chief Engineer, Army of the Potomac; A ledger letterbook contains copies of letters sent and received by Duane in his official capacity, 1864 July 3-1865 June 15. 1864 May-1865 Jun (Box 10)
    Of interest are a letter from General Meade 1864 July 3 requesting Duane's opinion on whether an attack is feasible; Meade's orders of July 9 concerning a siege of Petersburg; Duane's plan of operation July 10; Duane's opinion that a mine assault would fail due to flanking artillery fire, July 24; Duane's deposition on the failure of the attack, July 30; and Duane's opinion on the feasibility of proposed night attacks on the Petersburg defenses, 1865 March. Pontoon bridges are also a frequent topic.